<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lecture>
  <metadata>
    <week>4</week>
    <topic>Self-Managed Learning</topic>
    <duration>90 minutes</duration>
    <slide_count>30</slide_count>
  </metadata>

  <slide number="1" layout="big-number" title="Hook">
89%

of teachers worldwide believe "learning styles" (VARK, Kolb) improve learning outcomes

Scientific studies supporting this: 0

(Newton &amp; Salvi, 2020; Pashler et al., 2008)

<speaker-notes>
Let the statistic sit for 3 seconds. This is one of education's most persistent myths—nearly 9 out of 10 educators believe something science has thoroughly debunked. This isn't about teachers being wrong, it's about how persistent intuitive-but-false ideas can be. Today we'll learn what ACTUALLY works for learning. Have you ever been told you're a "visual learner" or "hands-on learner"? That feels true, doesn't it? But matching instruction to your "style" doesn't improve learning. This is a perfect example of why we need METACOGNITION—thinking about thinking, and evaluating claims critically.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="2" layout="section-break" title="Course Introduction">
# Self-Managed Learning
## Taking Control of Your Own Development

Week 4: Personal &amp; Professional Development

<speaker-notes>
Learning how to learn is perhaps the most valuable meta-skill for your career. In the AI era, continuous learning isn't optional—it's survival. This week connects everything: self-awareness (Week 5), reflection (Week 3), and your PDP (Week 11). You'll learn frameworks used at Stanford, Wharton, and other top business schools. More importantly, you'll learn what neuroscience and educational psychology have proven WORKS. Top performers don't just work harder—they work smarter by understanding HOW they learn.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="3" layout="content" title="Learning Objectives">
## Today's Learning Objectives

By the end of this lecture, you will be able to:

1. Apply Zimmerman's Cyclical Phase Model to your own learning
2. Use the Waterloo four-step SDL framework to create a learning contract
3. Evaluate the evidence for learning styles using the meshing hypothesis
4. Implement evidence-based learning strategies in your study habits

<speaker-notes>
These aren't just academic concepts—you'll use them THIS WEEK. LO1: You'll identify which phase (forethought/performance/self-reflection) you're weakest in. LO2: You'll create an actual learning contract for your PDP goal. LO3: You'll understand why learning styles feel right but don't work. LO4: You'll replace ineffective study habits with proven strategies. By Friday, you'll prepare for Mentor Meeting #2 using the four-step SDL process. By next week, you'll be using retrieval practice instead of just rereading. These objectives will appear on this week's quiz—write them down.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="4" layout="framework" title="Assessment Connection">
## How This Prepares You

| Assessment | Weight | Today's Relevance |
|------------|--------|-------------------|
| Mentor Meeting #2 | Part of 20% | Use SDL framework to set learning goals |
| Personal Development Plan | 40% | Learning strategies section + goal monitoring |
| Reflective Essay | 10% | Metacognitive analysis of field trip/speaker |
| Final Oral Exam | 30% | Demonstrate self-awareness of learning process |

Self-regulated learning is a PDP rubric criterion

<speaker-notes>
Your next mentor meeting happens in the next 2 weeks—today's content directly prepares you. Mentor Meeting #2 focus: Discuss your self-directed learning goals using the four-step framework. PDP Section 4: Learning strategies and monitoring approaches (Zimmerman's model provides structure). Reflective Essay: Metacognitive awareness deepens your analysis of experiences. When you write "I will improve my presentation skills" in your PDP, the SDL framework helps you turn that into an actionable learning contract with assessment milestones.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="5" layout="section-break" title="Roadmap">
# Today's Journey

1. Zimmerman's Self-Regulated Learning Model (25 min)
   The three-phase cycle that governs effective learning

2. Waterloo's Self-Directed Learning Framework (15 min)
   Four practical steps for taking ownership

3. The Learning Styles Myth (15 min)
   Why the meshing hypothesis fails—and what works instead

4. Evidence-Based Learning Strategies (20 min)
   Retrieval practice, spaced learning, elaboration, interleaving

5. Preparing for Mentor Meeting #2 (10 min)
   Applying SDL to your development goals

<speaker-notes>
We're covering A LOT today, but it all connects into a coherent system. Parts 1-2: Theoretical frameworks that organize HOW learning happens. Part 3: Critical thinking applied to popular beliefs. Part 4: Practical techniques you can use immediately. Part 5: Direct application to your mentorship.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="6" layout="section-break" title="Part 1 Title">
# Part 1
## Zimmerman's Self-Regulated Learning Model

The cyclical process of effective learning

<speaker-notes>
Barry Zimmerman's 2002 model has over 3,000+ citations. It's THE foundational framework for understanding self-regulated learning. Self-regulated learning (SRL) = consciously planning, monitoring, and evaluating your learning. This isn't something you "have" or "don't have"—it's teachable. The model has three interconnected phases that cycle continuously. Think about learning to drive: you plan your practice (forethought), monitor your steering (performance), then reflect on what went wrong (self-reflection)—then the cycle repeats.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="7" layout="framework" title="The Three-Phase Cyclical Model">
## Zimmerman's Cyclical Phase Model

┌─────────────────┐
│   FORETHOUGHT   │ ← Goal setting, planning, self-efficacy
└────────┬────────┘
         │
         ↓
┌─────────────────┐
│   PERFORMANCE   │ ← Self-control, self-observation
└────────┬────────┘
         │
         ↓
┌─────────────────┐
│ SELF-REFLECTION │ ← Self-judgment, self-reaction
└────────┬────────┘
         │
         └──────────→ [cycle repeats]

Learning is not linear—it's a continuous improvement loop

<speaker-notes>
This cycle happens whether you're aware of it or not. Effective learners CONSCIOUSLY manage all three phases. Forethought: What you do BEFORE learning (planning, motivation). Performance: What you do DURING learning (focus, monitoring). Self-Reflection: What you do AFTER learning (evaluation, response). Bad student: Shows up to class with no preparation, passively listens, never reviews. Good student: Reviews last week's notes (forethought), actively tests themselves during study (performance), identifies what they still don't understand (self-reflection). Which phase do YOU think you're weakest in?
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="8" layout="framework" title="Phase 1 - Forethought">
## Forethought Phase
What happens BEFORE learning

### Task Analysis
- Goal Setting: "I will master Excel pivot tables by Friday"
- Strategic Planning: "I'll watch tutorials, practice with sample data, then apply to my project"

### Self-Motivation Beliefs
- Self-Efficacy: "I CAN learn this—I've learned harder things before"
- Outcome Expectations: "This skill will help me in my internship"
- Intrinsic Interest: "Data analysis is actually pretty cool"
- Learning Goal Orientation: "I want to understand WHY, not just memorize steps"

<speaker-notes>
Forethought is where most students fail—they skip planning and jump straight to "studying". Task Analysis: Breaking down WHAT you need to learn and HOW you'll learn it. Goal Setting: Specific, measurable, realistic (we'll cover SMART goals in Week 11). Strategic Planning: Choosing methods BEFORE you start (not just opening the textbook and hoping). Self-Motivation: Your beliefs about your ability affect your performance (growth mindset from Week 9). Weak forethought: "I'll study for the test" (vague, no plan). Strong forethought: "I'll review lecture slides Monday, practice problems Tuesday-Wednesday, take practice test Thursday, review mistakes Friday" (specific, strategic).
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="9" layout="framework" title="Phase 2 - Performance">
## Performance Phase
What happens DURING learning

### Self-Control Strategies
- Imagery: Visualizing the process or outcome
- Self-Instruction: Talking yourself through steps
- Attention Focusing: Eliminating distractions (Week 8: Deep work)
- Task Strategies: Using proven techniques (more on this later)

### Self-Observation
- Self-Recording: "I've completed 15 out of 30 practice problems"
- Self-Experimentation: "Does studying in the morning work better for me than at night?"

<speaker-notes>
Performance phase is where effort meets strategy. Self-Control: Managing your focus, environment, and internal state during learning. Attention Focusing: Your phone is the enemy of this phase (Newport's Deep Work). Task Strategies: WHICH techniques you use matter—we'll cover this in Part 4. Self-Observation: Metacognitive monitoring = being aware of your understanding WHILE you learn. Low self-control: Studying with Netflix on, phone notifications pinging, stopping every 10 minutes for snacks. High self-control: Phone in another room, 25-minute Pomodoro timer, deliberate practice on hardest concepts first. Elite athletes use imagery and self-instruction constantly—"head down, follow through, watch the ball". You can do the same: "Read the question carefully, identify the framework, structure before writing."
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="10" layout="framework" title="Phase 3 - Self-Reflection">
## Self-Reflection Phase
What happens AFTER learning

### Self-Judgment
- Self-Evaluation: "How well did I understand the material?"
- Causal Attribution: "I did poorly BECAUSE I didn't practice enough" (not "because I'm bad at math")

### Self-Reaction
- Self-Satisfaction/Affect: Feeling proud of progress or frustrated with gaps
- Adaptive vs. Defensive Responses:
  - Adaptive: "I'll try a different strategy next time"
  - Defensive: "This material is stupid anyway" or "The teacher can't explain things"

<speaker-notes>
This is the MOST skipped phase—and the most valuable. Self-Evaluation: Accurately judging your understanding (calibration—more on this in Part 4). Causal Attribution: Fixed mindset blames ability ("I'm not a math person"), growth mindset identifies controllable factors ("I need better practice strategies"). Adaptive Responses: Effective learners adjust their approach based on results. Defensive Responses: Ineffective learners protect their ego instead of learning. After a bad quiz grade—Defensive: "The questions were unfair" / "I'm just bad at tests". Adaptive: "I need to practice retrieval instead of just rereading" / "I'll start studying earlier next time". Week 3 (Reflection): Gibbs' Cycle and Kolb's Cycle are STRUCTURED self-reflection processes. Week 9 (Growth Mindset): Attribution theory—do you attribute failure to fixed traits or adjustable strategies?
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="11" layout="content" title="The Cyclical Nature">
## Why It's a CYCLE, Not a Checklist

Example: Learning to Give Presentations

1. Forethought: "I'll practice 5 times, film myself, get feedback from 2 friends"
2. Performance: Deliver presentation, focus on eye contact and pacing
3. Self-Reflection: "I rushed the ending, lost eye contact when nervous"
4. Forethought (Round 2): "Next presentation, I'll practice the ending more, mark eye contact cues on slides"
5. Performance (Round 2): Apply lessons learned...
6. [Cycle continues]

Each cycle makes you better

<speaker-notes>
This is how mastery happens—through repeated cycles of improvement. Your self-reflection from one cycle INFORMS your forethought for the next. This is how top performers in ANY field improve: athletes, musicians, professionals. The cycle can happen in minutes (during a study session) or months (across a semester). Your PDP is essentially a long-term SRL cycle: Forethought: Setting 1-3-5 year goals. Performance: Executing learning strategies throughout your career. Self-Reflection: Annual reviews, mentor check-ins, adjusting goals. Reflective Essay: You're analyzing TWO cycles—field trip experience and guest speaker experience. Mentorship: Each meeting is a self-reflection phase that informs your next forethought. Where are you in the cycle right now for this course?
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="12" layout="section-break" title="Part 2 Title">
# Part 2
## Waterloo's Self-Directed Learning Framework

Four practical steps for taking ownership

<speaker-notes>
While Zimmerman gives us theory, Waterloo gives us a step-by-step process. Self-Directed Learning (SDL) emphasizes AUTONOMY—you choose what, when, how. This framework is used at top universities worldwide for independent study. You'll use this TODAY to prepare for Mentor Meeting #2.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="13" layout="framework" title="The Four-Step SDL Process">
## University of Waterloo's 4-Step Framework

### Step 1: Assess Readiness to Learn
Evaluate your current skills, attitudes, and motivation

### Step 2: Set Learning Goals
Create specific, measurable objectives (learning contracts)

### Step 3: Engage in the Learning Process
Identify resources, select strategies, actively participate

### Step 4: Evaluate Learning
Reflect on progress, seek feedback, adjust approach

(University of Waterloo Centre for Teaching Excellence, n.d.)

<speaker-notes>
Notice how this maps to Zimmerman's model—Step 1-2 = Forethought, Step 3 = Performance, Step 4 = Self-Reflection. This framework is especially useful when YOU get to choose what to learn (electives, skill development, PDP goals). Learning contracts (Step 2) make vague goals concrete. Step 4 closes the loop—you don't just learn, you EVALUATE what you learned. PDP Goal: "Improve my data analysis skills". Step 1: Assess—"I know basic Excel, weak on statistics, no experience with R or Python". Step 2: Goal—"Complete DataCamp Excel course by October, analyze 3 real datasets". Step 3: Engage—"30 min/day practice, apply to class projects, join data club". Step 4: Evaluate—"Did I finish the course? Can I clean and visualize data independently?"
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="14" layout="content" title="Learning Contracts">
## What Is a Learning Contract?

A learning contract is a written agreement (with yourself or a mentor) specifying:

1. WHAT you will learn (specific competencies)
2. HOW you will learn it (strategies and resources)
3. WHEN you will complete it (timeline with milestones)
4. HOW you will demonstrate learning (evidence/assessment)

Used in medical schools, MBA programs, and professional development

<speaker-notes>
Learning contracts turn fuzzy intentions into concrete commitments. They create ACCOUNTABILITY—especially when shared with a mentor. They force you to think strategically about HOW you'll learn (not just WHAT). They provide built-in evaluation criteria—you know if you succeeded or failed. Example: LEARNING CONTRACT: Public Speaking Skills. WHAT: Deliver a confident 10-minute presentation without reading slides. HOW: Join Toastmasters, attend 4 meetings; Practice 1 presentation/week with roommate feedback; Film myself, analyze body language and vocal variety. WHEN: 8 weeks (October 1 - November 26). EVIDENCE: Deliver group presentation without notes; Self-rating 4/5 on confidence; Peer feedback confirms engagement. Your PDP should include learning contracts for 1-year goals. Mentor Meeting #2: Share a learning contract and get mentor input.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="15" layout="section-break" title="Part 3 Title">
# Part 3
## The Learning Styles Myth

Why VARK doesn't work—and what does

<speaker-notes>
This will challenge something you've probably believed for years. That's uncomfortable—but it's important. Learning styles (VARK, Kolb) are one of education's most persistent "neuromyths". The idea FEELS right—but feelings aren't evidence. Understanding why this myth persists teaches you critical evaluation skills.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="16" layout="content" title="The Learning Styles Claim">
## The "Meshing Hypothesis"

Claim: Students learn better when instruction matches their preferred learning style

Examples:
- Visual learners should receive diagrams and videos
- Auditory learners should receive lectures and discussions
- Kinesthetic learners should receive hands-on activities

Predicted Result: Matching instruction to style → Better learning outcomes

<speaker-notes>
This is called the "meshing hypothesis"—mesh instruction to style. It seems intuitively obvious, right? Most of us have taken a VARK quiz or heard "I'm a visual learner". The claim requires EVIDENCE: Does matching improve learning MORE than just using multiple modalities? The prediction is testable—and has been tested extensively. If you're a "visual learner" and I teach you with diagrams, will you learn MORE than if I teach you with text? More importantly, will you learn MORE than a "verbal learner" getting the same diagrams? How many of you have been told you have a learning style? How many have seen evidence that matching instruction to it helps?
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="17" layout="content" title="What the Research Shows">
## The Scientific Consensus

### Pashler et al. (2008) - Comprehensive Review
Psychological Science in the Public Interest

Finding: "We found virtually no evidence for the interaction pattern" required to validate the meshing hypothesis

Translation: Matching instruction to learning style does NOT improve outcomes

### Newton &amp; Salvi (2020) - Teacher Beliefs Study
89-90% of teachers worldwide believe in learning styles despite lack of evidence

### Coffield et al. (2004) - Systematic Review
Identified 71 different learning styles models with major validity and reliability problems

<speaker-notes>
This isn't one study—it's decades of research across multiple fields. Pashler's review is considered THE definitive analysis—it's devastating to the meshing hypothesis. The problem isn't that people don't HAVE preferences—it's that matching instruction to preferences doesn't HELP. 71 models! If learning styles were real, there'd be consensus on what they are. Why It Persists: It feels true (confirmation bias); It's been taught for 50+ years (cultural inertia); Testing companies profit from it; It sounds student-centered and progressive. Imagine if medical schools taught 71 different models of the circulatory system—you'd know something was wrong. That's what happened with learning styles.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="18" layout="content" title="Why Matching Doesn't Work">
## The Problem With "Styles"

### 1. Content Matters More Than Style
- You can't learn to identify birds without SEEING birds (visual)
- You can't learn pronunciation without HEARING sounds (auditory)
- The content determines the optimal modality, not the learner

### 2. Preferences ≠ Effectiveness
- You might PREFER reading, but TESTING yourself is more effective
- "I'm a hands-on learner" often means "I get bored with lectures" (motivation, not cognitive style)

### 3. Effective Learning Uses MULTIPLE Modalities
- Best teaching: Visual + Verbal + Practice (for ALL students)

<speaker-notes>
The fundamental error is thinking learner characteristics override content characteristics. Content-Driven: Some things MUST be visual (anatomy diagrams), some MUST be verbal (poetry analysis). Preference ≠ Performance: Students often prefer methods that feel easy but produce shallow learning (rereading) over methods that feel hard but produce deep learning (self-testing). Multimodal Teaching: Good teaching uses diagrams AND explanations AND practice—for everyone. You can't learn to play guitar by reading about it (must be kinesthetic). You can't learn Excel by watching videos—you must practice. But EVERYONE learns guitar the same way: observe, practice, get feedback, repeat. When students study with their "preferred" style, they FEEL like they learned more—but perform the same or WORSE on tests (metacognitive illusion).
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="19" layout="section-break" title="Part 4 Title">
# Part 4
## Evidence-Based Learning Strategies

What cognitive science has proven ACTUALLY works

<speaker-notes>
Good news: We know exactly what works—it's just not what you've been doing. These strategies have HUNDREDS of studies supporting them. They work for all subjects, all ages, all people. They feel harder than passive review—but that's WHY they work (desirable difficulty).
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="20" layout="content" title="Strategy #1 - Retrieval Practice">
## Retrieval Practice (Self-Testing)

What It Is:
- Actively recalling information from memory (without looking at notes)
- Examples: Flashcards, practice tests, self-quizzing, explaining to a friend

Why It Works:
- The act of RETRIEVING strengthens memory more than passive review
- Identifies what you DON'T know (metacognitive benefit)

How to Use:
- After reading a chapter, close the book and write down everything you remember
- Use flashcards (Anki, Quizlet) for definitions and concepts
- Explain the lecture to a study partner without notes

Research: Dunlosky et al. (2013) rated practice testing as HIGH utility

<speaker-notes>
This is THE most powerful learning strategy—and most students don't do it. Retrieval Strengthens Memory: Every time you force yourself to recall, you reinforce the neural pathway. Identifies Gaps: You discover what you DON'T know—passive rereading creates illusion of knowledge. Testing Effect: Has been replicated in hundreds of studies across ages and subjects. Weak study session: Read chapter 3 times, highlight key points. Strong study session: Read once, close book, write summary from memory, check what you missed, quiz yourself on missed points. Students feel they need to "study more" before testing themselves—WRONG. Test yourself EARLY and OFTEN, even when you don't feel ready. This week's quiz: Use practice retrieval BEFORE taking it. PDP: Include retrieval practice in your learning strategy section.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="21" layout="content" title="Strategy #2 - Spaced Practice">
## Spaced Practice (Distributed Practice)

What It Is:
- Spreading study sessions over time (days/weeks) instead of cramming

Why It Works:
- Memory consolidation happens during sleep and between sessions
- Forcing yourself to re-retrieve after forgetting strengthens long-term retention

How to Use:
- Study Topic A on Monday, review on Wednesday, review on Sunday, review next week
- Start preparing for exams 2+ weeks early with daily 30-min sessions (not 6 hours the night before)
- Use a spaced repetition app (Anki) that automatically schedules reviews

Research: Dunlosky et al. (2013) rated distributed practice as HIGH utility

<speaker-notes>
This directly contradicts what most students do—cramming. Cramming Works Short-Term: You can pass a test the next day—but forget everything in a week. Spacing Works Long-Term: Initial performance seems slower, but retention is far superior. Desirable Difficulty: Re-learning after forgetting feels hard—that struggle is what strengthens memory. Cram: Study 8 hours Saturday night for Monday test → Pass test, forget by next month. Space: Study 1 hour/day for 8 days → Same test performance, retain for months/years. Cramming = running a sprint—fast but unsustainable. Spacing = training for a marathon—builds lasting capacity. Your PDP goals span 1-5 years—spaced practice, not cramming. Reflective Essay: Start thinking about field trip insights NOW, revisit weekly, write when it's due.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="22" layout="content" title="Strategy #3 - Elaboration">
## Elaboration (Deep Processing)

What It Is:
- Asking "why" and "how" questions to connect new information to existing knowledge

Why It Works:
- Creates richer, more interconnected memory networks
- Transforms surface-level memorization into deep understanding

How to Use:
- Elaborative Interrogation: "WHY does this make sense? HOW does this connect to X?"
- Self-Explanation: Talk through problems step-by-step, explaining your reasoning
- Connecting to Experience: "How have I seen this in real life?"

Research: Dunlosky et al. (2013) rated elaboration as MODERATE utility

<speaker-notes>
This is about UNDERSTANDING, not just memorizing. Surface Learning: "Metacognition = thinking about thinking" [memorizes definition]. Deep Learning: "Metacognition is like being aware of my own thought process—it's how I caught myself making assumptions in the field trip reflection". Transfer: Elaboration helps you APPLY knowledge in new contexts (not just recognize it on multiple-choice tests). Reading Zimmerman's model: Don't just memorize the three phases. ASK: "When have I used forethought in my own learning? What happens when I skip the self-reflection phase? How does this connect to Gibbs' Reflective Cycle from Week 3?" Tutorial today: You'll elaborate on your learning strategies. Reflective Essay: Elaboration = connecting field trip to course concepts (Week 1, 5, 7, 9). Right now, elaborate: How does spaced practice connect to Zimmerman's self-reflection phase?
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="23" layout="content" title="Strategy #4 - Interleaving">
## Interleaving (Mixed Practice)

What It Is:
- Mixing different types of problems or topics during study (instead of blocking by type)

Why It Works:
- Forces you to actively choose the right strategy for each problem (metacognitive practice)
- Improves discrimination between problem types

How to Use:
- Instead of: 10 algebra problems, then 10 geometry problems
- Try: Algebra, geometry, algebra, calculus, geometry, algebra...
- Mix subjects during study sessions (30 min accounting, 30 min marketing, 30 min statistics)

Research: Dunlosky et al. (2013) rated interleaving as MODERATE utility

<speaker-notes>
This feels HARDER and less efficient—but that's the point. Blocked Practice: Feels easy, creates illusion of mastery (you're pattern-matching, not thinking). Interleaved Practice: Feels difficult, forces you to THINK about which approach to use. Transfer Benefit: Interleaving helps you recognize problem types on exams where they're mixed. Blocked: All Week 1 quiz questions, all Week 2 quiz questions, all Week 3... Interleaved: Mix Week 1, 3, 5, 2, 7, 4 questions—forces you to IDENTIFY which framework to use. When to Use: Later stages of learning (not when totally new to a concept); Practicing for exams that mix topics; Maintaining multiple skills over time. Your Reflective Essay mixes concepts from Weeks 1-10—interleaved application. PDP integrates self-assessment, goal-setting, skills development—interleaved competencies.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="24" layout="framework" title="What Works vs. What Doesn't">
## Evidence-Based Summary

### ✅ HIGH EVIDENCE (Use These)
- Retrieval Practice - Self-testing, flashcards, explaining without notes
- Spaced Practice - Distribute study over time
- Elaboration - Ask why/how, connect to existing knowledge
- Interleaving - Mix problem types during practice

### ⚠️ LOW EVIDENCE (Use Sparingly)
- Highlighting/Underlining - Passive, doesn't engage memory
- Rereading - Creates false sense of familiarity
- Summarizing - Only helps if you're trained in the technique

### ❌ NO EVIDENCE (Stop Doing)
- Matching instruction to learning styles - Myth

(Dunlosky et al., 2013; Stanton et al., 2021)

<speaker-notes>
Notice what's missing from the "works" list—most of what students actually DO. Students overwhelmingly use LOW-EVIDENCE strategies (highlighting, rereading) because they feel easy. HIGH-EVIDENCE strategies feel harder—that's desirable difficulty. Your study time is limited—invest it in strategies that actually work. 3 hours of highlighting and rereading &lt; 1 hour of retrieval practice and spaced review. Connection to Self-Regulated Learning: Forethought: Choose evidence-based strategies BEFORE you start studying. Performance: Implement retrieval/spacing/elaboration/interleaving. Self-Reflection: Did these strategies improve your test performance? Adjust if needed. Which low-evidence strategy do YOU use most often? Which high-evidence strategy will you try THIS WEEK?
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="25" layout="section-break" title="Part 5 Title">
# Part 5
## Preparing for Mentor Meeting #2

Applying SDL to your development goals

<speaker-notes>
Everything today points to this: Your next mentor meeting focuses on self-directed learning. Meeting #2 recommended focus: "Learning goals and progress monitoring". You'll create a learning contract for ONE PDP goal. Your mentor will help you refine your strategies and hold you accountable.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="26" layout="content" title="Meeting #2 Preparation Checklist">
## Preparing for Mentor Meeting #2

### Before the Meeting (Pre-Meeting Form - Due 48 Hours Before)

1. Assess Your Learning Readiness (Waterloo Step 1)
- What's one skill/competency you WANT to develop for your career?
- What's your current level? (1-10 scale + specific evidence)
- What motivates you to improve this? (Connect to PDP goals)

2. Draft a Learning Contract (Waterloo Step 2)
- WHAT: Specific competency/skill
- HOW: Strategies you'll use (include evidence-based techniques)
- WHEN: Timeline with milestones
- EVIDENCE: How you'll know you've improved

3. Prepare Discussion Questions
- "Does this learning goal align with my career path?"
- "What resources or strategies have you used for similar skills?"
- "How will I know if I'm making progress?"

<speaker-notes>
The better your preparation, the more value you get from mentor time. Your mentor is NOT a teacher—they're a guide. Come with a DRAFT, not a blank page—mentors refine ideas, they don't create them for you. The Pre-Meeting Form is assessed—take it seriously. Example Learning Contract: WHAT: Improve data storytelling for business presentations. HOW: Take DataCamp "Data Visualization" course (6 hours, complete by Oct 15); Practice: Create 3 visualizations for group project, get peer feedback; Apply: Use in Group Presentation (Week 12). WHEN: 6 weeks (Oct 1 - Nov 15). EVIDENCE: Complete course with 80%+ on quizzes; Group presentation includes 3 clear, impactful visuals; Self-rating improvement from 4/10 to 7/10. This learning contract becomes Section 4 of your PDP (due Week 11). Meeting #2 Post-Reflection Form: Document mentor advice and how you'll apply it.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="27" layout="section-break" title="Summary">
# What We Covered Today

1. Zimmerman's SRL Model: Forethought → Performance → Self-Reflection (cycle repeats)

2. Waterloo's SDL Framework: Assess readiness → Set goals → Engage → Evaluate

3. Learning Styles Myth: Meshing hypothesis has no evidence; content drives modality, not learner "style"

4. Evidence-Based Strategies: Retrieval practice, spaced practice, elaboration, interleaving

5. Mentor Meeting #2 Prep: Create a learning contract using today's frameworks

<speaker-notes>
This is A LOT—don't try to memorize it, try to APPLY it. The frameworks connect: SDL operationalizes SRL. The myth-busting matters: Critical evaluation of educational claims. The strategies work: Replace ineffective habits with proven techniques. Starting today, test yourself instead of rereading. Starting this week, space your study instead of cramming. Starting this month, create a learning contract for your PDP. Which concept will be hardest to apply? Why?
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="28" layout="content" title="Return to Learning Objectives">
## Did You Achieve Today's Objectives?

Self-Check:

1. ✅ Can you explain Zimmerman's three phases and identify your weakest one?
2. ✅ Can you use the Waterloo framework to create a learning contract?
3. ✅ Can you explain why the meshing hypothesis is unsupported?
4. ✅ Can you name four evidence-based strategies and commit to using one?

If YES to all four: You're ready for the tutorial and quiz

If NO to any: Review the slides, attend office hours, discuss with peers

<speaker-notes>
Honest self-assessment (metacognition in action!). These objectives are on this week's quiz. Tutorial will give you hands-on practice with learning contracts and strategy audits. This content directly supports your PDP and Reflective Essay. This is hard material—it challenges how you've studied your whole life. That discomfort means you're learning.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="29" layout="content" title="Before Next Class">
## Your Action Items

### 📝 This Week
1. Tutorial: Complete learning strategy audit and draft learning contract
2. Quiz: Week 4 Quiz on Moodle (Zimmerman, Waterloo, learning styles, evidence-based strategies) - Due Sunday 11:59 PM
3. Mentor Meeting #2: Schedule within next 2 weeks, submit Pre-Meeting Form 48 hours before

### 📚 Next Week Preview
- Week 5: Self-Discovery Through Assessment
- Readings: MBTI, VIA Character Strengths, Holland Code, Johari Window
- You'll complete 4 self-assessment tools and integrate insights

### 💡 Apply Immediately
- Try ONE evidence-based strategy this week (retrieval practice recommended)
- Reflect: Did it feel harder? Did it work better?

<speaker-notes>
Learning doesn't stop when class ends—it's just beginning. Tutorial is hands-on practice—bring your PDP ideas. Quiz reinforces today's concepts—use retrieval practice to study for it! Mentor Meeting #2 is where theory becomes action. Week 5's self-assessments (MBTI, VIA, Holland Code) build on your self-awareness. Your PDP is taking shape—you're 1/3 through the course. The best learners aren't the smartest—they're the most strategic. You now have the strategies. Use them.
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

  <slide number="30" layout="content" title="Questions?">
# Questions?

Office Hours: By appointment - wil.hoang@gmail.com

Resources:
- Lecture slides on Moodle
- Readings in course folder
- Tutorial materials distributed today

Remember: Self-regulated learning is a SKILL, not a trait. You can improve it with practice.

<speaker-notes>
Take 5-10 minutes for questions. Encourage students to try ONE strategy this week and report back. Common Questions: "Do learning styles not matter AT ALL?" → Preferences exist, but matching doesn't improve learning; good teaching uses multiple modalities for everyone. "What if cramming has worked for me?" → Define "worked"—did you retain the knowledge? Could you apply it weeks later? "How do I convince myself to use harder strategies?" → Start small (one flashcard session), experience the results, build the habit. See you in tutorial. Come ready to design your learning contract!
</speaker-notes>
  </slide>

</lecture>
