<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lecture week="9" title="Cross-Cultural &amp; Team Communication">

<slide number="1" layout="big-number" title="89% of White-Collar Workers Complete Projects in Global Virtual Teams">

Yet 95% of research focuses on what goes wrong.

Today: Learn what makes cross-cultural teams succeed.

**Source:** CultureWizard (2018); Taras et al. (2021)

<speaker-notes>
**Opening:**
Start by asking students: "How many of you have worked with team members from different countries or cultural backgrounds?"

"Today we're going to challenge the assumption that cultural diversity is always a problem to overcome—research shows it can be your competitive advantage"

**Key Points:**
89% statistic from global study of 5,728 individuals across 804 teams in 90 countries. Most research until recently focused on negative diversity effects—this is changing. Vietnamese students increasingly work in multinational companies (Samsung, Intel, Microsoft) where cross-cultural skills are essential.

**Example:**
Samsung Vietnam employs 160,000+ workers with Korean management teams—understanding power distance and feedback culture directly affects promotion prospects.

**Transition:**
Let's build the frameworks to turn these challenges into strengths.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="2" layout="content" title="Today's Learning Objectives">

By the end of this lecture, you will be able to:

1. **Apply** Hofstede's cultural dimensions to analyze communication challenges across cultures
2. **Design** communication strategies for virtual teams using psychological safety principles
3. **Evaluate** feedback approaches using Meyer's Three A's framework
4. **Create** team communication protocols that leverage contextual diversity

<speaker-notes>
Four concrete skills you'll practice in today's tutorial and use in your Week 12 Group Presentation. LO1 = Foundation (understanding the framework), LO2 = Virtual context (your reality as students and professionals), LO3 = Practical application (giving/receiving feedback), LO4 = Assessment connection (team protocols for presentations).

**Example:**
By next week, when you start preparing your group presentations, you'll have tools to manage time zones, feedback styles, and decision-making preferences.

**Transition:**
Let's connect these skills to what you'll be graded on.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="3" layout="framework" title="How This Prepares You for Group Presentation (Week 12)">

**Today → Week 12 Journey:**

| Week | Focus | How Today Helps |
|------|-------|-----------------|
| **9 (Today)** | Cross-cultural frameworks | Understand team diversity as asset |
| **10** | Capstone integration | Apply all frameworks to presentation prep |
| **11** | Review &amp; practice | Rehearse with cultural awareness |
| **12** | Group Presentation | Deliver with confident team dynamics |

**Graded Components Using Today's Skills:**
- **Group Presentation (25%):** Team coordination, role clarity, seamless transitions
- **Individual Grade (15%):** Your contribution within diverse team context

<speaker-notes>
Your group presentations are just 3 weeks away—today's frameworks directly prepare you. Most students form groups with friends = similar backgrounds; real workplaces = diverse teams. Your individual grade depends partly on how well you coordinate with teammates. Cultural dimensions affect: who speaks first, how you give feedback on drafts, how you make decisions about content.

**Example:**
If your group has both Vietnamese and international students, understanding high vs. low power distance helps you create equal speaking opportunities. Virtual team principles apply even if you meet in person—you'll coordinate via Zalo, email, shared docs.

**Transition:**
Let's see how the top business schools prepare students for these exact situations.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="4" layout="section-break" title="Today's Journey">

**Part 1: Cultural Dimensions in Communication** (25 min)
- Hofstede's 6 dimensions
- Vietnamese cultural profile
- Communication implications

**Part 2: Building Psychological Safety in Teams** (20 min)
- Edmondson's framework
- The Learning Zone
- Virtual team applications

**Part 3: Cross-Cultural Feedback** (20 min)
- Meyer's Three A's
- Upgraders vs. downgraders
- Case studies

**Part 4: Leveraging Team Diversity** (15 min)
- Personal vs. contextual diversity
- Evidence from 804 global teams
- Action protocols

<speaker-notes>
Four distinct segments—we'll pause between each for quick reflection. Part 1 = The "what" (dimensions framework), Part 2 = The "why" (safety enables performance), Part 3 = The "how" (practical feedback delivery), Part 4 = The "so what" (turning knowledge into action).

**Example:**
Think of this as building blocks: first understand cultural differences, then create safe environment, then practice specific skills, finally apply to your teams.

**Transition:**
Let's start with the most cited framework in cross-cultural business communication.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="5" layout="section-break" title="Part 1: Cultural Dimensions in Communication">

Understanding the invisible forces shaping how we communicate

<speaker-notes>
Culture is like water to fish—we don't notice it until we encounter a different culture. Geert Hofstede's research = 117,000 IBM employees across 40 countries (later 76 countries). Most influential framework in cross-cultural business—taught at every M7 business school. 33,000+ citations on Google Scholar; Wall Street Journal Top 20 business thinker (2008).

**Example:**
Hofstede started at IBM in the 1960s and noticed that management practices that worked in the US failed in Japan—not because of poor execution, but because of cultural assumptions.

**Transition:**
Here's the vocabulary to describe those differences precisely.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="6" layout="quote" title="Culture: The Collective Programming of the Mind">

> "Culture is the collective programming of the mind distinguishing the members of one group or category of people from others."
>
> — Geert Hofstede (2001)

**Key Insight:** Culture is learned, not innate—it can be understood and navigated.

<speaker-notes>
Culture = shared mental software acquired from social environment (family, school, workplace). Not about individuals—about group patterns and averages. Culture changes slowly (across generations) but does change. Understanding your own cultural programming is the first step to navigating others'.

**Example:**
Vietnamese students often wait for instructor to call on them rather than raising hands spontaneously—this isn't shyness, it's culturally programmed respect for hierarchy. American students often interrupt with questions—this isn't rudeness, it's culturally programmed emphasis on individual participation.

**Transition:**
Hofstede identified 6 dimensions where cultures systematically differ.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="7" layout="framework" title="Hofstede's Six Cultural Dimensions">

| Dimension | Low Score Cultures | High Score Cultures |
|-----------|-------------------|---------------------|
| **Power Distance** | Hierarchy for convenience | Hierarchy reflects inequality |
| **Individualism** | "We" identity, loyalty | "I" identity, autonomy |
| **Masculinity** | Caring for others valued | Achievement valued |
| **Uncertainty Avoidance** | Comfortable with ambiguity | Need for rules and structure |
| **Long-Term Orientation** | Respect for tradition | Adaptation and persistence |
| **Indulgence** | Gratification restrained | Gratification encouraged |

**Key Principle:** Cultures are *relative* to each other—no dimension is inherently good or bad.

<speaker-notes>
These are sliding scales from 0-100, not binary categories. Power Distance (PDI): How much less powerful members accept unequal distribution. Individualism (IDV): Degree to which people integrate into groups. Masculinity (MAS): Distribution of values between achievement and caring (dated term, but standard in research). Uncertainty Avoidance (UAI): Society's tolerance for uncertainty and ambiguity. Long-Term Orientation (LTO): Focus on future rewards vs. past/present. Indulgence (IVR): Freedom to enjoy life and have fun.

**Example:**
Vietnam scores HIGH on power distance—respect for hierarchy. USA scores HIGH on individualism—individual achievement prioritized. Neither is better—both have strengths and costs.

**Transition:**
Let's look at Vietnam's specific profile.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="8" layout="framework" title="Vietnam on Hofstede's Dimensions">

| Dimension | Vietnam Score | Interpretation |
|-----------|--------------|----------------|
| **Power Distance** | 70 (High) | Hierarchical society; managers expect obedience |
| **Individualism** | 20 (Low—Collectivist) | Strong "we" identity; group harmony valued |
| **Masculinity** | 40 (Moderate) | Balance between competition and care |
| **Uncertainty Avoidance** | 30 (Low) | Comfortable with ambiguity; flexible rules |
| **Long-Term Orientation** | 57 (Moderate-High) | Values persistence and adaptation |
| **Indulgence** | 35 (Restrained) | Work before pleasure; self-discipline valued |

**Communication Implications:**
- Indirect disagreement (preserve harmony)
- Respect seniority in speaking order
- Comfortable with flexible plans
- Focus on long-term relationships

<speaker-notes>
High PDI + Low IDV = Vietnamese students often hesitate to challenge instructors or senior colleagues. Low UAI = Paradoxically, Vietnamese are comfortable with ambiguity and last-minute changes (despite high PDI). Moderate LTO = Values both respect for elders (past) and adaptation (future). These are averages—individuals vary widely.

**Example:**
In Vietnamese companies, junior staff often say 'Em xin phép' (I humbly ask permission) before speaking—this signals respect for hierarchy. In Australian companies, calling your boss by first name and disagreeing directly is normal—low power distance.

**Transition:**
Now let's compare Vietnam to cultures your classmates or future colleagues might come from.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="9" layout="framework" title="How Vietnam Compares: Four Cultural Profiles">

| Dimension | Vietnam | USA | Japan | Germany |
|-----------|---------|-----|-------|---------|
| Power Distance | 70 | 40 | 54 | 35 |
| Individualism | 20 | 91 | 46 | 67 |
| Masculinity | 40 | 62 | 95 | 66 |
| Uncertainty Avoidance | 30 | 46 | 92 | 65 |
| Long-Term Orientation | 57 | 26 | 88 | 83 |
| Indulgence | 35 | 68 | 42 | 40 |

**Biggest Contrasts:**
- **Vietnam vs. USA:** Power distance (70 vs. 40), Individualism (20 vs. 91)
- **Vietnam vs. Japan:** Uncertainty avoidance (30 vs. 92), Masculinity (40 vs. 95)
- **Vietnam vs. Germany:** Individualism (20 vs. 67), Long-term orientation (57 vs. 83)

<speaker-notes>
These four countries represent major business partners for Vietnam—Samsung (Korea/similar to Japan), Intel (USA), Bosch (Germany). Vietnam-USA clash: Americans expect direct feedback and individual initiative; Vietnamese expect indirect cues and group consensus. Vietnam-Japan clash: Japanese want detailed plans before action; Vietnamese adapt as they go. Vietnam-Germany clash: Germans value individual accountability; Vietnamese value collective responsibility. Notice Japan and Germany are both "Western" but very different from each other—culture ≠ geography.

**Example:**
American manager to Vietnamese team: 'What do YOU think we should do?' (expects individual opinion). Vietnamese team member thinks: 'Why is the manager asking me? They should decide and tell us' (expects hierarchy). Both are confused, neither is wrong—just different PDI programming.

**Transition:**
These dimensions directly affect how we give and receive feedback—let's see three real cases.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="10" layout="content" title="Case Study: When Direct Feedback Backfires">

**Context:** Olga, Ukrainian HR executive, relocates to West Virginia for US operations

**Challenge:** Used to giving direct feedback in Ukraine:
- "This absolutely cannot continue"
- "Reply-all" emails with criticism
- Immediate correction of mistakes in meetings

**What Happened:**
- American team felt attacked and "bullied"
- Complaints to senior leadership
- Olga confused: "I'm just being honest and efficient"

**Cultural Analysis:**
- Ukraine (PDI 92, UAI 95): Direct feedback signals respect and seriousness
- USA (PDI 40, IDV 91): Direct criticism threatens individual face; use "sandwich method"

**Lesson:** Even "Western" cultures differ dramatically in feedback directness

**Source:** Meyer (2023), "When Diversity Meets Feedback," *Harvard Business Review*

<speaker-notes>
Olga wasn't being mean—she was using Ukrainian professional norms. Americans weren't being oversensitive—they were expecting American professional norms. Both Ukraine and USA are "Western" and "direct communicators" but differ on EVALUATING dimension (feedback). This shows Hofstede's dimensions are just starting point—need more nuanced frameworks too.

**Example:**
In Vietnamese context: Olga's approach would be even more shocking because high PDI = face-saving is critical. Imagine Vietnamese employee receiving 'This absolutely cannot continue' in front of peers—devastating.

**Transition:**
Let's see the opposite problem—American manager in Asia.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="11" layout="content" title="Case Study: When 'Constructive' Feedback Offends">

**Context:** Jethro, American VP, gives performance review via video to Thai team member

**What Jethro Said:**
- "Here are three areas where you're excelling"
- "Here are two areas for improvement: [specific details]"
- "Let's make a development plan for the next quarter"

**What Happened:**
- Thai employee filed complaint for "bullying"
- Thai HR intervened: "You cannot criticize people directly"
- Jethro shocked: "I followed the best practice feedback model!"

**Cultural Analysis:**
- USA (IDV 91): Direct feedback = respect for growth and development
- Thailand (PDI 64, Collectivist): Direct criticism = loss of face; "say the good, leave out the bad"

**Adaptation:**
- Thai HR taught Jethro: "Praise what's good, imply what needs improvement through questions"
- Example: "Your reports are thorough. What would make them even more impactful for executives?"

**Lesson:** "Best practice" = culturally specific

**Source:** Meyer (2023), "When Diversity Meets Feedback," *Harvard Business Review*

<speaker-notes>
Jethro used the "sandwich method" (positive-negative-positive) taught in US business schools. Even this was too direct for Thai context where harmony > individual development. Thailand (similar to Vietnam) = high context, indirect communication, face-saving critical. Notice Jethro had good intentions and training—still failed because of cultural gap.

**Example:**
Vietnamese equivalent: Instead of 'Your presentation needs better structure,' say 'Your content is strong; I'm wondering how we might guide the audience's attention even more clearly'. The message is the same, but the delivery preserves face and group harmony.

**Transition:**
One more case—this time about WHEN to give feedback, not just how.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="12" layout="content" title="Case Study: When Feedback Violates Power Dynamics">

**Context:** Cassandra, female software VP, delivers keynote presentation

**What Happened:**
- Male colleague Miles (her peer) sends detailed email next day
- "Here are five tips to improve your presentations:"
- Lists: vocal variety, pause techniques, slide design suggestions
- Signs off: "Hope this helps!"

**Cassandra's Reaction:**
- Felt self-confidence "hijacked"
- Advice was technically correct but completely unrequested
- "I've been presenting for 15 years—why does he think I need his coaching?"

**The Hidden Issue:**
- **Gender + Power Dynamics:** Research shows men give unrequested advice to women 5× more than to other men
- **Violates "Ask First" principle** (covered in next section)

**Lesson:** Even actionable, well-intentioned feedback can damage relationships when power dynamics are ignored

**Source:** Meyer (2023), "When Diversity Meets Feedback," *Harvard Business Review*

<speaker-notes>
This case isn't about national culture—it's about gender culture and power. Miles probably thought he was being helpful and collegial. 90%+ of women report receiving unsolicited advice from male colleagues. Men rarely give unrequested advice to other men at same level. This intersects with cultural dimensions: in high PDI cultures, junior advising senior is unthinkable. Even in low PDI cultures (like USA), gender and seniority matter.

**Example:**
Imagine Vietnamese context: Would a junior male employee email unsolicited presentation tips to a senior female leader? Never—hierarchy prevents it. But what about two peers of different genders? Research shows the pattern persists globally.

**Transition:**
These three cases show why we need structured frameworks for cross-cultural feedback—let's learn one.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="13" layout="section-break" title="Part 2: Building Psychological Safety in Teams">

Why some teams enable voice and others silence it

<speaker-notes>
Quick recap: we've learned WHAT cultural differences exist. Now: WHY do some diverse teams thrive despite differences? Amy Edmondson's psychological safety = most important predictor of team success. Google's Project Aristotle studied 180 teams: psychological safety = #1 factor. 92,000+ citations for Edmondson's work—taught at Harvard, Stanford, all M7 schools. Psychological safety ≠ trust, ≠ niceness, ≠ low standards.

**Example:**
Two Vietnamese students working on group project with two international students. Low safety: Vietnamese students stay quiet in meetings, do extra work alone to avoid speaking up. High safety: All four openly say 'I'm confused about the deadline' or 'I disagree with this approach'.

**Transition:**
Here's Edmondson's precise definition.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="14" layout="quote" title="What Is Psychological Safety?">

> "A shared belief held by members of a team that the team is safe for interpersonal risk taking."
>
> — Amy C. Edmondson (1999)

**Not the Same As:**
- ❌ Trust (expectations about others' future actions)
- ❌ Group cohesiveness (can reduce willingness to challenge)
- ❌ "Being nice" (safety enables the candid feedback that niceness avoids)

**Key Insight:** Safety is about the *team climate*, not individual relationships.

<speaker-notes>
"Shared belief" = everyone on team feels it; not just leader-to-member but peer-to-peer. "Interpersonal risk taking" = asking questions, admitting mistakes, challenging status quo, offering wild ideas. Distinction from trust: trust = "I believe you'll keep your word"; safety = "I believe the team won't punish me for speaking up". Distinction from cohesiveness: very cohesive teams can have groupthink; safety requires comfort with disagreement.

**Example:**
Vietnamese university group: high cohesiveness (everyone friends), low safety (no one challenges others' ideas). Workplace team: moderate cohesiveness (cordial but not friends), high safety (vigorous debates in meetings). Which produces better work? Research shows the second one.

**Transition:**
Edmondson created a framework showing psychological safety isn't enough alone.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="15" layout="framework" title="The Four Zones: Safety × Accountability">

|  | **Low Accountability** | **High Accountability** |
|---|---|---|
| **High Psychological Safety** | **Comfort Zone**<br/>Safe but complacent<br/>No pressure to perform | **Learning Zone** ⭐<br/>Optimal performance<br/>Innovation + execution |
| **Low Psychological Safety** | **Apathy Zone**<br/>Minimal effort<br/>"Why bother?" | **Anxiety Zone**<br/>Fear-driven work<br/>Burnout + politics |

**Your Group Presentation Goal:** Create Learning Zone (high safety + high accountability)

**How:**
- High safety: Everyone can propose ideas without judgment
- High accountability: Everyone delivers on commitments

<speaker-notes>
Comfort Zone: Nice team, no standards = no growth (common in student projects where everyone is friends). Anxiety Zone: High standards, fear of speaking up = burnout (common in high-pressure corporate cultures). Apathy Zone: Nobody cares about quality or climate = worst outcome. Learning Zone: The sweet spot—people challenge each other AND support each other. Vietnamese teams often start in Anxiety Zone (high PDI = fear of senior/leader) or Comfort Zone (collectivism = harmony over candor).

**Example:**
Comfort Zone: Your group meets, everyone says 'looks good,' nobody revises, presentation is mediocre. Learning Zone: Your group meets, someone says 'I think our argument is weak here,' team debates, everyone revises, presentation is excellent.

**Transition:**
How do leaders create Learning Zone? Edmondson has a three-step process.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="16" layout="framework" title="Three Leadership Practices for Psychological Safety">

**1. Set the Stage**
- Frame work as *learning problem*, not execution problem
- Acknowledge your own fallibility as leader
- "I don't have all the answers—I need everyone's input"

**2. Invite Participation**
- Ask proactive questions: "What are we missing?"
- Design structures for input (anonymous surveys, round-robin)
- Create space for quiet voices

**3. Respond Productively**
- Express appreciation even for critical feedback
- Destigmatize failure: "What did we learn?"
- Offer help and solutions, not blame

**Cultural Note:** These practices work globally but require adaptation—e.g., high PDI cultures need extra emphasis on "Set the Stage" to overcome hierarchy.

<speaker-notes>
These aren't just for managers—anyone can create safety in their group. Set the Stage = Permission: Vietnamese students especially need explicit permission to speak up because high PDI. Invite Participation = Structure: Don't just say "any questions?"—use specific prompts and wait time. Respond Productively = Modeling: The first time someone challenges an idea, how you respond determines whether others will. In Vietnamese context: "Set the Stage" means saying "I want us to be in Learning Zone—please question my ideas".

**Example:**
Bad response to challenge: "That won't work because [dismissive reasons]" → silence for rest of project. Good response: "That's a great question—I hadn't considered that angle. Let's explore it together."

**Transition:**
Psychological safety enables cross-cultural teams to leverage their diversity—let's see the research.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="17" layout="section-break" title="Part 3: Cross-Cultural Feedback Mastery">

Erin Meyer's practical framework for giving feedback across cultures

<speaker-notes>
We've seen WHAT cultural dimensions exist and WHY safety matters. Now: HOW to give feedback across cultures. Erin Meyer = INSEAD professor, author of *The Culture Map*. Her "Three A's" framework = practitioner favorite (simpler than Hofstede, more actionable). Based on 20+ years consulting with global companies. Featured in INSEAD executive program "Leading Across Borders and Cultures".

**Example:**
You'll use this framework in tutorial today and in Week 12 when giving feedback to teammates on presentation drafts.

**Transition:**
Here's Meyer's framework for getting feedback right.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="18" layout="framework" title="The Three A's of Effective Cross-Cultural Feedback">

**1. Aim to Assist**
- Give feedback *only* with genuine intention to help
- NEVER to vent frustration or assert dominance
- Check your motivation before speaking

**2. Actionable**
- Must include clear actions recipient can take
- If no action exists, withhold the feedback
- Vague criticism helps no one

**3. Ask First**
- Request feedback on your own work before giving feedback to others
- Balances power dynamics
- Creates reciprocal culture

**The Golden Rule, Revised:**
"Do unto others as *they* would have done unto themselves"—not as *you* would want it.

**Source:** Meyer (2023), "When Diversity Meets Feedback," *Harvard Business Review*

<speaker-notes>
Three simple rules that prevent 90% of cross-cultural feedback disasters. Aim to Assist: Cassandra case violated this—Miles aimed to show expertise, not genuinely help. Actionable: "Your presentation wasn't engaging" = useless; "Pause 3 seconds after key points to let them land" = actionable. Ask First: Solves the Cassandra problem—if Miles had asked "Want feedback on your presentation style?" she could decline. Vietnamese context: "Ask First" is culturally aligned with high PDI (respects hierarchy and face-saving).

**Example:**
Violates all three: "Your slides are terrible" (not actionable, probably not aiming to assist, unrequested). Follows all three: "I'm working on my slide design—would you be willing to exchange feedback? Here are two specific things I'd love your input on in my deck."

**Transition:**
Even when you follow the Three A's, HOW you phrase feedback matters enormously across cultures.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="19" layout="framework" title="Cultural Language Patterns: Upgraders vs. Downgraders">

| **Direct Feedback Cultures** (Use Upgraders) | **Indirect Feedback Cultures** (Use Downgraders) |
|---|---|
| **Countries:** Germany, Netherlands, Russia, Israel | **Countries:** Thailand, Japan, Indonesia, Vietnam |
| **Language Patterns:** "absolutely," "totally," "completely wrong" | **Language Patterns:** "kind of," "a little bit," "maybe," "sort of" |
| **Philosophy:** Clarity = respect; directness = professionalism | **Philosophy:** Harmony = respect; indirectness = professionalism |
| **Criticism Style:** State the problem plainly | **Criticism Style:** "Say the good, leave out the bad" |

**The Counterintuitive Insight:**
- Americans = LOW-context communicators but INDIRECT with negative feedback
- French = HIGH-context communicators but DIRECT with criticism

**Implication:** You must map cultures on BOTH dimensions (communicating + evaluating).

**Source:** Meyer (2014), *The Culture Map*

<speaker-notes>
This explains why the same feedback feels helpful to Germans and insulting to Thais. "Upgraders" intensify the message ("This is totally unacceptable"). "Downgraders" soften the message ("This is maybe not quite ideal"). Both cultures understand the message—but emotional impact differs drastically. Vietnamese students using English: avoid upgraders when giving feedback to international peers. Vietnamese students receiving feedback from Germans/Dutch: don't personalize their directness.

**Example:**
German to Vietnamese: "This structure is completely wrong" (meant as helpful clarity). Vietnamese hears: "You're incompetent" (feels devastating). Vietnamese to German: "Perhaps we might consider a slightly different approach" (meant as face-saving). German hears: "Sounds fine, no action needed" (misses the criticism).

**Transition:**
Let's see Meyer's full framework positioning countries on two dimensions.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="20" layout="framework" title="Where Countries Fall: Direct vs. Indirect Feedback">

**Most Direct Negative Feedback:**
1. Netherlands, Germany
2. Russia, France, Israel
3. Spain, Italy
4. USA, Canada, Australia
5. UK, Singapore
6. Brazil, Mexico, India
7. China, Japan, Vietnam, Thailand

**Most Indirect Negative Feedback**

**Key Insight for Vietnamese Students:**
- Vietnam = indirect feedback culture (position 7)
- Most international business contexts = more direct (positions 1-5)
- Adapt your style to be more explicit when working with Western cultures
- Use downgraders when working with other Asian cultures

**Practical Rule:**
- More direct than your culture → add softeners ("I wonder if we might consider...")
- More indirect than your culture → add clarity ("Specifically, I suggest...")

**Source:** Meyer (2014), *The Culture Map*

<speaker-notes>
Position is RELATIVE to other cultures—there's no "absolute" directness. Vietnam clusters with Thailand and Japan at indirect end. Notice USA is in the middle (position 4)—more direct than Vietnam, less direct than Germany. Singapore is interesting—more direct than other Asian countries because of British colonial influence. Your Group Presentation: if mixing Vietnamese and Western students, establish explicit norms.

**Example:**
Vietnamese student giving feedback to German student: 'I think we should restructure Section 2 to put the conclusion first' (direct for Vietnamese, still too indirect for German). Better: 'Section 2 needs restructuring. I recommend moving the conclusion to the opening paragraph. Can we revise by Friday?'

**Transition:**
These frameworks apply powerfully to virtual teams—let's see why.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="21" layout="section-break" title="Part 4: Leveraging Team Diversity">

Why contextual diversity outperforms homogeneity

<speaker-notes>
Final segment: putting it all together for your group presentations. Most students fear diversity = more work and conflict. Research: contextual diversity (different backgrounds) = BETTER outcomes. Study: 5,728 individuals, 804 teams, 90 countries—largest global virtual team study ever. Finding: diverse teams produced higher-quality work than homogeneous teams.

**Example:**
Your group with Vietnamese + international students has a potential advantage over all-Vietnamese group. Why? Different perspectives catch blind spots.

**Transition:**
But not all diversity works the same way—let's distinguish types.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="22" layout="framework" title="Two Types of Diversity: Different Effects">

| Diversity Type | Definition | Primary Impact | Effect on Performance |
|---|---|---|---|
| **Personal Diversity** | Individual characteristics: age, gender, race, personality | **Psychological outcomes**<br/>(satisfaction, cohesion, conflict) | ⚠️ Can be negative without active management |
| **Contextual Diversity** | Background factors: country, industry, functional expertise, education | **Task outcomes**<br/>(quality, creativity, innovation) | ✅ Positive—diverse perspectives improve solutions |

**Key Research Finding:**
"Teams with higher contextual diversity produced higher-quality consulting reports, and their solutions were more creative and innovative."

**Implication:** Leverage contextual diversity (different majors, work experiences, countries) as competitive advantage.

**Source:** Taras et al. (2021), "How Cultural Differences Can Impact Global Teams," *Harvard Business Review*

<speaker-notes>
This distinction is crucial—not all diversity is equally challenging or beneficial. Personal diversity: Visible/demographic differences → affects team climate and trust. Contextual diversity: Background and expertise differences → affects work quality. Research shows contextual diversity benefits typically outweigh personal diversity challenges. But: personal diversity needs active management (this is where psychological safety comes in). Your group projects: leverage contextual (different strengths, perspectives) while managing personal (communication styles).

**Example:**
Contextual diversity example: Vietnamese student studied marketing, American student studied finance, Thai student worked in tech startup → each brings unique lens to business problem. Personal diversity challenge: Different communication styles cause misunderstandings → needs explicit team norms.

**Transition:**
So how do we maximize contextual diversity's benefits while managing personal diversity's challenges?
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="23" layout="big-number" title="The Two Cultural Factors That Predict Team Success">

**Most Important for Positive Team Outcomes:**

1. **Gender Egalitarianism** (HIGH = better outcomes)
   - Equal voice regardless of gender
   - Challenge: 90%+ women report receiving unsolicited advice from men
   - Action: Establish "Ask First" norm

2. **Absence of Power Distance** (LOW PDI = better outcomes)
   - Flat hierarchy in team interactions
   - Challenge: Vietnamese culture = high PDI
   - Action: Explicitly invite junior members to speak first

**Why These Two?**
Both enable *psychological safety*—the #1 predictor of team effectiveness.

**Source:** Taras et al. (2021), "How Cultural Differences Can Impact Global Teams," *Harvard Business Review*

<speaker-notes>
Of all Hofstede's dimensions, two stand out for team performance. Gender egalitarianism = everyone's ideas valued equally regardless of gender. Low power distance = junior members feel comfortable challenging senior members. Both create conditions for psychological safety → Learning Zone. Vietnamese teams face structural challenge: high PDI is cultural norm. Solution: EXPLICITLY create low PDI environment within team ("We're operating as equals in this project").

**Example:**
Problem: Vietnamese group, oldest member's ideas automatically accepted without debate. Solution: "Let's use round-robin: youngest member shares first, then next youngest, etc." Problem: Female team members hesitate to disagree with male members. Solution: "Before voting, everyone writes their position anonymously, then we reveal."

**Transition:**
Let's end with practical protocols you can implement immediately.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="24" layout="framework" title="Practical Team Communication Protocols">

**Protocol 1: First Meeting—Establish Cultural Norms**
- Share: "I'm from [culture], we tend to [communication style]"
- Decide: "For this project, we'll use [explicit norms]"
- Example: "We'll use Meyer's 'Ask First' before giving feedback"

**Protocol 2: Leverage Contextual Diversity**
- Assign roles based on different strengths: research, design, speaking, logistics
- Each person leads one aspect where they have unique expertise
- Rotate presentation sections so everyone's voice is heard

**Protocol 3: Create Psychological Safety**
- Use Edmondson's "Set the Stage": "We're in Learning Zone—challenge ideas, not people"
- Invite participation: "What are we missing?" not "Any questions?"
- Respond productively: "Great point—I hadn't thought of that"

**Protocol 4: Adapt Feedback Style**
- Map your team on Meyer's scales
- Vietnamese members: add more directness when working with Western members
- Western members: add more softening when working with Asian members

<speaker-notes>
Copy these four protocols to use in your Week 10 group meeting. Protocol 1: Explicit > implicit; don't assume everyone shares your norms. Protocol 2: This is how you leverage contextual diversity. Protocol 3: This is how you build psychological safety. Protocol 4: This is how you navigate cultural dimensions. These aren't optional "nice-to-haves"—research shows they predict team performance.

**Example:**
First meeting script: 'I'm Vietnamese, our culture is indirect with feedback, so if I seem hesitant to criticize, that's why—please push me to be more explicit'. Western student: 'I'm American, we're direct even when giving negative feedback, so if I seem blunt, I'm not being rude—please tell me if I should soften my language'.

**Transition:**
Let's wrap up today's journey.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="25" layout="content" title="Key Takeaways: Cross-Cultural &amp; Team Communication">

**Framework Mastery:**
1. **Hofstede's Dimensions:** Power distance and individualism explain most communication differences between Vietnam and Western cultures
2. **Psychological Safety:** High safety + high accountability = Learning Zone (your goal)
3. **Meyer's Three A's:** Aim to assist, make it actionable, ask first
4. **Diversity Types:** Leverage contextual (backgrounds), manage personal (demographics)

**Practical Application:**
- Vietnam = high PDI, collectivist, indirect feedback → adapt to more direct style with Western collaborators
- Use explicit team protocols (don't assume shared norms)
- Create psychological safety before expecting open communication

**For Week 12 Group Presentation:**
Establish norms early, leverage each member's unique strengths, practice feedback across cultural styles

<speaker-notes>
Four frameworks, dozens of applications—but they all connect. These frameworks aren't just academic—they're used by McKinsey, Google, Samsung, every major multinational. Your competitive advantage in Vietnamese job market: ability to navigate cross-cultural teams. These skills matter whether you work in Vietnam for multinational or abroad. 89% of white-collar work involves global teams—this is baseline professional skill now.

**Example:**
Next time you're in meeting and notice someone isn't speaking up, ask: Is this a PDI issue (hierarchy)? A feedback culture issue (fear of criticism)? A psychological safety issue (team climate)? Then you can intervene strategically: 'Let's hear from [quiet person] first before the rest of us chime in'.

**Transition:**
Let's connect this to your assessments.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="26" layout="framework" title="Coming Up: Group Presentation (Week 12)">

**How Today's Content Helps:**

| Group Presentation Component | Today's Framework |
|---|---|
| **Team coordination** | Psychological safety protocols |
| **Role clarity** | Leveraging contextual diversity |
| **Seamless transitions** | Practice giving/receiving feedback |
| **Handling Q&amp;A** | Cross-cultural communication adaptation |

**This Week's Tasks:**
1. **Tutorial:** Practice cross-cultural feedback with team simulation
2. **Online Quiz:** Hofstede dimensions, Meyer's Three A's, psychological safety
3. **Group Meeting:** Establish team protocols using today's frameworks

**Timeline:**
- Week 10: Capstone integration &amp; final prep
- Week 11: Rehearsal with feedback
- Week 12: Presentations!

<speaker-notes>
Three weeks until presentations—today's frameworks are your team coordination toolkit. Your individual grade (15%) partly based on how well you work within your team. Examiners watch for: equal participation, smooth handoffs, unified message. These require: psychological safety, explicit norms, cultural adaptation. Students who use today's protocols score higher on both group and individual grades.

**Example:**
Low-performing team: No explicit norms, quiet members never speak, awkward transitions. High-performing team: Visible protocols ("We're using round-robin for decisions"), all members contribute equally, smooth flow. The difference is applying today's frameworks.

**Transition:**
Looking ahead to next week.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="27" layout="section-break" title="Next Week: Integration &amp; Capstone">

**Week 10 Topic:** Synthesizing course learning for final presentation

**What We'll Cover:**
- Bringing together Weeks 1-9 frameworks
- Presentation rehearsal strategies
- Self-assessment and development planning
- Final executive summary (last portfolio piece)

**Connection to Today:**
Week 10 applies today's team communication frameworks to your actual group dynamics as you prepare final presentations.

**Preparation:**
- Form final presentation groups by end of this week
- Hold first meeting using today's protocols
- Begin brainstorming presentation topics

<speaker-notes>
Week 10 = capstone week, bringing everything together. Next week is synthesis, not new frameworks. You'll reflect on your communication growth across the semester. Last portfolio piece (Executive Summary) due Week 10. Week 11 = review and quiz, then Week 12 = presentations.

**Example:**
Think of today as tools, next week as application of tools. If today is learning to use a hammer and saw, next week is building the actual house.

**Transition:**
Finally, here are resources for deeper learning.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

<slide number="28" layout="content" title="Additional Resources">

**Interactive Tools:**
- **Hofstede Country Comparison:** hofstede-insights.com/product/compare-countries/
- **Culture Map Assessment:** erinmeyer.com (self-assessment tools)
- **CQ Assessment:** culturalq.com (Cultural Intelligence test)

**Essential Reading:**
- Meyer, E. (2014). *The Culture Map* (Full book—practical guide)
- Edmondson, A. C. (2019). *The Fearless Organization* (Building psychological safety)
- Taras et al. (2021). "How Cultural Differences Can Impact Global Teams" (*HBR*)

**Video Resources:**
- Amy Edmondson's TEDx on psychological safety (12 min)
- Erin Meyer's INSEAD lectures (YouTube)

**For Vietnamese Students:**
- Research on Vietnamese business culture: Ashwill &amp; Diep (2005), *Vietnam Today*
- Vietnamese workplace norms: Dana (1999), *Conflict Resolution*

**All articles from today's lecture available on course Moodle page.**

<speaker-notes>
Everything cited today is accessible—most is free or in library. Hofstede and Meyer tools are interactive—plug in any country pair. CQ assessment is paid but has free sample. All HBR articles accessible through university library. Vietnamese context resources help you translate frameworks to local reality.

**Example:**
Before your next group meeting, everyone do Culture Map self-assessment and share results—takes 10 minutes, incredibly revealing. For tutorial today, you'll use Hofstede comparison tool.
</speaker-notes>

</slide>

</lecture>
